Hillcrest Children's Center (Washington, D.C.) Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Unbound Records, 1815-1966 (Boxes 1-33)
  - 14th and S Street property
    - Lots appropriated by Congress
      - General data, 1832-1861, 743 TAF
      - Square 246, 1842-1843, 744 TAF
      - Square 244, 1855-1856, 745 TAF
      - Square 400, 1848-1859, 1869, 1885, 746 TAF
      - Square 282, 1848-1858, 747 TAF
      - Square 128, 1846-1888, 748 TAF
      - Square 259, 1843-1890, 749 TAF
    - James Hall estate dispute over possession of lots, 1895-1897, 750 TSF
    - Barbour property, 1870-1888, 761 TCF
    - Myrtle Street, 1871-1902, 762 TCF
    - Suggested purchase of farm, 770 ODF
    - 14th Street extended
      - Purchase of property, 1899-1907, 771 TSF
      - Grading, dedication of street, 1900-1901, 772 TSF (Box 24)
      - Property, proposed building, 1902-1914, 773 TSF
      - Condemnation case, 1920-1921, 774 TSF
      - Rejected offer of purchase, 1921, 775 TSF
      - Real estate appraisals, 1921, 776 TSF
      - Sales of property, 1922-1926, 777 TSF
      - Deferred purchase trust, 1923-1926, 1943, 778 TSF
    - Proposed home site, 18th and Argyle Streets, 1918, 779 TSF
    - Rental property owned by WCOA, 1936-1948, 780 THF
    - Miscellaneous property
      - Lot sale, 1826, 790 OAE
      - Rents,etc., 1867-1891, undated, 791 TCF
      - Water rents, 1876-1891, 791.1 TCF
      - Condemnation of asylum property near Capitol, 792 TSF
      - Cemetery lots, 1854-1912, 793 OCF
      - Other property, 1912, 794 TSF
      - Union Station, effect on property, 1903-1905, 795 TSF
      - Other property, 1883-1925, 796 TCF
      - McNamara property (Lot 5, Sq. 790), 1870-1876, 797 TCF
      - Bills, receipts, etc.
        - 1864-1874, 798
        - 1875-1883, 798 (Box 25)
        - 1884-1892, 798 (Box 26)
        - 1898-1906, 798
        - 1916-1937, 798 (Box 27)
        - Undated, 798
  - Legacy and gift records
    - Legacies, miscellaneous, 800 TCF
    - Legacy
      - Deed and gift cards, 800.1 TCF
      - Ellsworth, Goodwin D., 1948, 800.2 LHF
      - Information list, 800.3 TCF
      - Acker, Nicholas, 1881, 801 TSF
    - Gift, Avalon Foundation, 1950, 801.1 LHF
    - Legacies
      - Bailey, Charles B., 1925-1929, 802
      - Baker, John A., 803 THF
      - Barrick, Clara A., 1927, 804 THF
      - Berman, Lillian Hunt, 1936-1937, 805 THF
      - Brashear, McLain, 1936-1940, 805.1 THF
      - Broadhead, Josephine, 1882, 806 TSF
      - Buchly, Anthony, 1899, 807 TSF (Box 28)
      - Carmack, Jeannette, 1900, 808 TSF
      - Casilear, Raphael, 1945-1946, 809 THF
      - Church, Charles, 1913, 810 TSF
      - Church, William A. H., 1931, 811 THF
      - Commonwealth Farm, 1903, 1946-1948, 812 TCF
      - Corcoran, W. W., 1897-1902, 1950, 812.1 TSF
      - Corning, William, 1872, 813 TDF
      - Cox, Juliet Haxeltine, 1932, 813.1 THF
      - Cox, George G., 1908-1910,1942-1943, 814 TSF
      - Crissey, Mabel E., 1946-1947, 815 THF
      - Devine, M. Virginia, 1938-1939, 815.1 THF
      - Duvall, Eliza Ann, 1869, 816 TDF
      - Eliza Ann Duvall's legatee, Clara Herbert, 1869-1872, 817 TDF
      - Duvall, Sarah Ann, 1866, 818 TAF
      - Edwards, Ann, 1880, 819 TSF
      - Eherbach (Eberbach), Henry, 1926, 820 THF
      - Eleanor Faison Sowers Memorial Library, 1943-1951, 820.1 OHF
      - Ford, Milton, 1893-1897, 821 TSF
      - Fraser, Daniel, 1922-1923, 822 TSF
      - Gantt, Georgiann, 1914-1915, 823 TSF
    - Gift
      - Gould, Edwin, 1926-1949, 824 THF
    - Legacies
      - Green, Sarah, 1910, 824.1 TSF
      - Hall, James C.
        - 1881-1884, 825 TSF
        - Land in Arkansas, 1911-1912, 826 TSF (Box 29)
        - Laurie Fund property, 1881-1900, 827 TSF
      - Hall, Mrs. S. A., 1869, 827.1 TDF
      - Highland Community Church, 1930-1931, 828.1 THF
      - Hurt, Annie, 829 THF
      - Ireland, Susan, 1870, 830 TDF
      - James, Matilda, 1920-1928, 830.1 TSF
      - Johnson, Lewis, 1875, 830.11 TDF
      - Kann, Simon, 1933, 830.2 THF
      - Kerr, Mary Ann, 1876-1879, 831 TDF
      - King, Charles B., 1879, 832 TSF
      - Lacy, Edward, 1876-1882, 832.1 TCF
      - Lacy's heir, Eliza McGlenen, 1876-, 833 TCF
      - Lansburgh, Henry, 1930-1931, 833.1
      - Lansburgh, Stanley, 1928, 834 THF
      - Lawrence, David M., 835 TSF
      - Lockwood, Homer N., 1915-1916, 835.1 TSF
      - Lowry, George, 1881, 836 TSF
      - Lucas, Anthony Francis, 1922, 837 TSF
      - Lucas, Melina, 837.1 THF
      - Marc, Charles, 1927-1948, 838 THF
      - Mayer, Theodore J., 1908, 1916, 839 TSF
      - McGlue, Amelia, 1932, 840 THF (Box 30)
      - McGuire, James, 1888, 841 TSF
      - Miller, Caroline, 1910-1915, 842 TSF
      - Morrison, David L., 1887-1888, 843 TSF
      - Morrison, Alexander, 1886,1933, 844 TSF
      - Moses, Zebena, 1918-1919, 845 TSF
      - Muchada, William, 1866, 846 TDF
      - Mullikin, Elizabeth H., 1919, 847 THF
      - Naval Lodge No. 4, 1865, 849 TAF
      - Nichols, Sally Lathrop, 1921-1926, 850 TCF
    - Gift
      - Old Dominion Foundation, 1950, 850.1 LHF
    - Legacies
      - Osborn, Mary Ellen, 1927-1932, 851 TCF
      - Otterback, Philip, 1885, 852 TAF
      - Owen, Edward, 1865, 853 TAF
      - Peugh, Caroline S., 1886, 854 TDF
      - Pierpont, Samuel S.
        - Miscellaneous, 855 TCF
        - Property, 1869-1885, 856 TCF
      - Pilling, Frederick, 1931, 857 TSF
      - Powell, J. Tyler, 1921, 858 TSF
      - Rhees, William Jones, 1907, 1910, 859 TSF
      - Rives (Reeves), Lucy, 1883, 860 TSF
      - Rutherford, Sophia L., 1927, 861 THF
      - Ryan, R. J., 1876-1883, 862 TSF
      - Saunders, Julia I., 1945-1948, 863 THF
      - Schafer, Charles, 1939-1940, 864 THF
      - Shanks, Catherine, 1880, 865 TSF
      - Shedd, James J., 1901, 866 TSF
      - Sibley, William, 1898-1900, 867 TSF (Box 31)
      - Sioussa (Siousi), Augustus T., 1868-1888, 868 TCF
      - Smith, Edward S., 1909-1941, 868.1 THF
      - Snow, Chester
        - Miscellaneous, 1919-1941, 869 TCF
        - Property, 1892, 1919-1927, 870 TCF
      - Stellwagen, Charles, 1908, 871 TSF
      - Stout, Julia M., 1927-1929, 872 THF
      - Stuhlinger, Eliza, undated, 873 TSF
      - Talbot, Laura Osborn, 1906, 873.1 TSF
      - Temple, Mary G., 1898, 874 TSF
    - Gift
      - Thompson, William, 1892, 875 TSF
    - Legacy
      - Walker, Marie L., 1882-1888, 1931-1933, 876 TSF
    - Gift
      - Washington Self Help Exchange, 1948, 876.1 LHF
    - Legacie
      - Watson, John M., 1932-1937, 877 THF
      - Weber, Charles, 1885, 878 TSF
      - Williamson, Matilda, 1902, 879 TSF
      - Wright, Jeannette B., 1896, 880 TSF
      - Wright, Mathew, 1868-1880, 881 TAF
    - Church collections and other gifts, 1906, 1931, 1949-1952, 890 OCF
    - WCOA beneficiary of insurance of Mrs. James Cox, 1934, 891 THF
  - Historical and miscellaneous records
    - Historical sketch of WCOA, 900 OCF
    - Newspaper excerpts compiled by Mrs. Cox, Mrs. Bates, and Mrs. Coleman, 910 LCR
    - History of Washington City Orphan Asylum (Box 32)
      - Typed copies of minutes, 1815-1869, 911 LCF
      - Transcript of minutes, 1815-1870, 911.1 LCF
    - Colt, Katherine Gideon, historical notes, minutes of annual meetings, 912 LCF
    - Historical notes and partial copies of minutes of annual meetings, 1870-1943, 912 LCF
    - Historical data on WCOA, 914 LCF
    - Excerpts compiled by Mrs. Coleman and Mrs. Cox, 920 OCF
    - Historical sketch of WCOA by Mrs. Coleman, 921 OHF
    - Financial and legal history, notes by Mrs. Coleman, 922
    - “Burns, David and Marcia,” by S. Helen Fields, 940 OAF
    - “The Good Fairy, Marcia Burns Van Ness,” by Ethel T. Howard, 941 LCF
    - W. W. Corcoran signature, 960 TCF
    - Busts and portraits, 1868-1953, 961 OCF
    - Publicity, presidents and first ladies of the United States, 962 OCF
    - Lion
      - Presentation, 1835, 970 OAE
      - Agent for auction, 1835, 971 OAE
      - Expenses, 1835, 972 OAE
      - Auction, account of, 1835, 973 OAE
      - Miss Colt's notes pertaining to, 974 OCF
    - Letters concerning need for new building, 1919, 1923, 980 OSF
    - Letters concerning reorganization, repairs, and equipment needed, 981 LSF (Box 33)
    - Reference library on American benefactions, 982 OHF
    - Archives, request for, 1966, 983 OHF
    - Requests for archival information, 983.1 OHF
    - Anniversaries and special occasions, 990 OCF
    - Automobiles, 1934-1946, 991 LHF
    - Newspaper clippings, 1960-1965, 992 OCF
    - Newspaper insertions, 992.1 OCF
    - Wilmington Orphan Asylum annual report, 1871, 993 ODF
    - Flag given to Hillcrest, 994 LHF
    - Washington Institute of Mental Hygiene
      - Minutes of meetings (Board of Managers), 1944-1960, 995
      - Reports, etc., 1936-1950, 995.1
      - Legacy of Gertrude D. Morris, 1964, 995.2
    - Financial accounts, old classification system, 998
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, notes, deeds, etc., 1835, 999
- Bound Records, 1815-1955 (Boxes 34-57)
  Journals, ledgers, minutes of meetings, financial statements, applications, relinquishments, check stubs, indentures, numerical index, and some correspondence.
  Numerically arranged and decimally cataloged. Some overlapping exists in the numerical order of the records in this series as a result of the binding arrangement. Includes oversize items.
  *Containers 34-35 are available on microfilm, shelf no. 21,372
  - Original constitution, Oct. 10, 1815, 110 (Box 34*)
  - Rules and regulations, Dec. 13, 1851, 111
  - Admission of children, Nov. 1815 -Sept. 1822, 210
  - Relinquishment of children, 1826-1829, 1833, 220
  - Minutes, Board of Lady Managers, 1815-1851, 310
  - Financial accounts of ladies, 1819-1825, 340
  - Donations and subscriptions, 1815-1827, 350
  - Annual reports, 1867-1955, 150-150.2 (Box 35*)
  - Original admissions of children, 1815-1880, 211 (Box 36)
  - Admissions of children, 1923-Feb. 1944, 213
  - Partial records of admissions, 1881-1897, 214
  - Records of children received and taken out, 1867-1870, 214.1 (Box 37)
  - Partial records, 1890-1910, 215
  - Relinquishment of children
    - 1835-1876, 221
    - 1876-1922, 222 (Box 38)
  - Application and family history (Box 39)
    - Oct. 1902-1906, 223
    - 1907-1923 (Oversize), 224 (Box OV 40)
  - Indentures for binding out children (Box 41)
    - 1858-1876, 251
    - 1877-1902, 252
    - 1904-1915, 253 (Box 42)
  - Adoptions, reference correspondence, 1870-1884, 1888-1893, 254
  - Adoptions, 1877-1915, 260 (Box 43)
  - Samuel, foundling, letter concerning, 1832, 290
  - Financial account of ladies, 1826-1851, 341
  - Donations and subscriptions, 1825-1851, 351
  - Minutes, Feb. 1851-Dec. 1863, 311 (Box 44)
  - Minutes, Board of Lady Managers, Jan. 1864-1877, 312
  - Financial accounts of ladies
    - 1852-1911, 342
    - 1911-1920, 343
  - Legal opinion of Richard S. Coxe, Apr. 6, 1857, 431
  - Minutes, Board of Lady Managers, 1878-1902, 313 (Box 45)
  - Minutes of ladies (missing), Dec. 1903-1904, 313.2
  - Minutes of board meetings, Jan. 1905-Dec. 1919, 314
  - Financial accounts of ladies, 1852-1911, 342
  - Minutes of the Board of Lady Managers (Box 46)
    - 1920-1939, 315
    - 1940-1946, 316
    - 1947-1953, 316.1 (Box 47)
  - Financial accounts of ladies
    - 1911-1920, 343
    - 1920-1928, 344
    - 1928-1933, 345 (Box 48)
  - Staff salaries, May 1923-Dec. 1933, 345.1
  - Servants' wages, May 1923-Sept. 1924, 345.2
  - Donations and subscriptions, 1851-1863, 352 (Box 49)
  - Donations, “beneficiaries,” 1939-1945, 354
  - First trustees' book of WCOA, 1833-1855, 500
  - Account book of receipts and expenditures, 1855-1857, 520.1 (Box 50)
  - Journal of Board of Trustees
    - May 1859-Feb. 1870, 522
    - Mar. 1870-Feb. 1874, 523
    - Jan. 1883-Nov. 1890, 526
    - Mar. 1892-June 1898, 529
    - Jan. 1888-Nov. 1891 (Oversize), 527 (Box OV 51)
  - Check stubs, Board of Trustees (Box 52)
    - Feb. 1894-Apr. 1906, 531
    - Apr. 1906-Oct. 1915, 532
  - Journal of Board of Trustees
    - Sept. 1909-Dec. 1926, 536
    - Jan. 1927-Dec. 1941, 537 (Box 53)
  - Memoranda of WCOA, 1874, by Edward Temple, 548
  - Ledger of Board of Trustees
    - Apr. 1859-Oct. 1873, 550
    - Nov. 1873-1892, 551
  - Ledger book (Box 54)
    - General and special funds, 1892-1927, 552
  - Account book
    - Laurie Fund, 1892-1916, 552.1-552.3
    - General fund, 552.4-552.7 (Box 55)
  - Ledger and journal (combined for Laurie Fund), Oct. 1881-Nov. 1890, 562
  - Notes held by the Board of Trustees, 1898-1937 (Oversize), 553 (Box OV 56)
  - Journal (Box 57)
    - Laurie Fund, Nov. 1890-Mar. 1892, 563
  - Dedication of hall, WCOA, 963
  - Visitors' book
    - “Little Museum, ” 1935-1938, 996
    - Hillcrest, 1938-1939, 997
    - Open house, 1947, 997.1
  - Index, numerical
- Miscellany (Oversize) (Boxes OV 58-OV 59)
  An alphabetical index, maintenance and beneficiary journal, and deed and schedule of lots donated by Congress in 1832.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Index, alphabetical (Box OV 58)
  - Hillcrest funds, maintenance, and beneficiary journals, 1932-1950, 347 (Box OV 59)
  - Deed and schedule of lots appropriated by Congress, 1832, 740-741